<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An elegie on the much lamented death of the Right Honorable Sir Arthur Chichester Knight, Lo. Baron of Belfast, Lo. high Treasurer of Ireland, one of the lords of His Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Counsell, and of the Counsell of Warre. By Alex Spicer..</title>
            <author>Spicer, Alexander, b. 1574 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117749</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852959</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852959</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18314</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12792)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18314)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1157:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An elegie on the much lamented death of the Right Honorable Sir Arthur Chichester Knight, Lo. Baron of Belfast, Lo. high Treasurer of Ireland, one of the lords of His Maiesties most Honorable Priuie Counsell, and of the Counsell of Warre. By Alex Spicer..</title>
                  <author>Spicer, Alexander, b. 1574 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 2, 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By M[iles] F[lesher] for Robert Bird, and are to be sold at his shop in Cheapeside at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chichester of Belfast, Arthur Chichester, --  Baron, 1563-1625 --  Death and burial --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18314:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18314:1"/>
            <p>AN ELEGIE ON THE MVCH LAMENTED DEATH OF THE RIGHT HONORABLE Sir <hi>Arthur Chicheſter</hi> Knight, Lo. Baron of <hi>Belfaſt, Lo. high Treaſurer of Ireland, one</hi> of the Lords of his Maieſties moſt Honorable Priuie Counſell, and of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Warre.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Honor ſequitur fugientem.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>By ALEX. SPICER.</p>
            <p>Printed at London by M.F. for Robert Bird, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Cheapeſide at the ſigne of the Bible. 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18314:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18314:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST NOBLE and moſt Illuſtrious <hi>George</hi> Duke of BVCKINGHAME his Grace, &amp;c.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SJr, like <hi>Parrhaſius,</hi> J haue thought it meete</l>
               <l>To draw the worke, J wrought on, in a <hi>ſheet:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If your quicke eye diſcerne vnhandſome feature,</l>
               <l>Where 'twas my part to limne a comely creature:</l>
               <l>Daigne to beleeue (my Lo.) my hand did ſhake,</l>
               <l>Becauſe much ſorrow made my heart to ake.</l>
               <l>Be then your gracious patience as the vaile</l>
               <l>To couer that, wherein my skill did faile.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt ſubmiſſiue and deuoted Orator. ALEX. SPICER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:18314:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18314:3"/>
            <head>An Elegie on the death of my <hi>Lord Chicheſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ead? and before we heard him ſicke, incline</l>
               <l>To draw his breath towards that vtmoſt line,</l>
               <l>Which leads to earth? this moues me to enquire,</l>
               <l>Why noble <hi>Belfaſt</hi> ſhould ſo ſoone expire.</l>
               <l>T'was thus, death knew that ſuch a gallant pray</l>
               <l>Could not be had vnles 'twere ſnatcht away:</l>
               <l>And therefore ſtrucke him in a deadly hower,</l>
               <l>Beyond recouerie by Phyſitians power.</l>
               <l>But we are bound to fame which keepes aliue</l>
               <l>This Noble-man, whom death would not repriue.</l>
               <l>Dead? with ſad throbs my fainting ſpirits trippe</l>
               <l>In ſorrowes maze, and by my mournefull lippe.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18314:4"/>
               <l>My teares make way to tell my heart 'tis ſo,</l>
               <l>And leaue deepe dints, like furrowes, as they go.</l>
               <l>The twines of all my hopes are riuell'd and</l>
               <l>Like to ſome pinnace in no hope to land</l>
               <l>At any port of ſafetie, altogether</l>
               <l>I lye expoſed vnto wracke of weather.</l>
               <l>The <hi>point</hi> I aim'd at was vntimely loſt</l>
               <l>Not in March Winds, but Februaries froſt:</l>
               <l>Noble <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> Ile hugge thine honoured worth,</l>
               <l>That in the warmth of it may iſſue forth</l>
               <l>Formes of perfection; to expreſſe thy beautie:</l>
               <l>Or if I faile in that, my humble dutie</l>
               <l>Shall kneele in publike to pin on a Verſe</l>
               <l>With trembling fingers on thy ſable Herſe,</l>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18314:4"/>
               <l>Which muſt be arched high, to ſtand aboue</l>
               <l>That Lord who filled all the world with loue.</l>
               <l>My muſe ſhall haue in charge to write of him,</l>
               <l>As a noble branch of an ennobled ſtemme.</l>
               <l>From <hi>Chicheſters</hi> diſcent he tooke his name,</l>
               <l>And in exchange of it, return'd ſuch fame</l>
               <l>By his braue deeds, as to that race ſhall be</l>
               <l>A radiant ſplendor for eternitie:</l>
               <l>For fame ſhall write this Adage, <hi>Let it laſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like the ſweet memorie of my Lord</hi> Belfaſt.</l>
               <l>When once the time of childhood did begin</l>
               <l>To ſtep aſide, that youth might enter enter in,</l>
               <l>He went to <hi>Oxford,</hi> that the liberall Arts</l>
               <l>Might be ennamel to his natiue parts.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18314:5"/>
               <l>Faire education with good parentage</l>
               <l>Made all his vertues walke in equipage,</l>
               <l>That they who knew him young, preſag'd his ſcope</l>
               <l>Was euer bending to that Cape of Hope</l>
               <l>Where Honour rides
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>He was a Captaine of the ſhip cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Lo. <hi>Sheffield,</hi> employed againſt the Spaniſh Inuaſion, <hi>Anno</hi> 1587, &amp; 88.</p>
                     <p>Afterwards he was Captaine and Commander in the Portugall voyage of 200. foot, in the Regiment of the Generall ſir <hi>Fra. Drake,</hi> 88. and 89.</p>
                     <p>He went with ſir <hi>Fra. Drake</hi> to the Weſt Indies, where he was Captain of a Companie of foot, and Lieutenant Colonell of a Regiment. And in Porterico he ſet fire of the Admirall of the Spaniſh Frigats, 95. &amp; 96.</p>
                     <p>After their return from that voyage, he was employed in France, being Captain and Lieutenant Colonel of a regiment with ſir <hi>Th. Baskeruile,</hi> 96</p>
                     <p>After his returne out of France, he was employed into Ireland with the Earle of Eſſex, &amp;c.</p>
                  </note>; For after he had ſeene</l>
               <l>The <hi>Muſes,</hi> he return'd to ſerue his Queene</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18314:5"/>
               <l>With armes of valour, the report of them</l>
               <l>May be a <hi>Chronicle:</hi> for ſo large a theame</l>
               <l>Requires a booke in <hi>Folio,</hi> not one leafe,</l>
               <l>To ſhew the homage due to <hi>Ioſephs Sheafe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All bow'd to his, and no worth finds extent</l>
               <l>Beyond the bounds of his, whom I lament.</l>
               <l>Graue, brane, ſure, pure, and like a heauenly ſtar,</l>
               <l>In peace, war, ſpeech, and life, was <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Renowmed Lord, whoſe noble acts yeeld matter</l>
               <l>For me to praiſe, and yet abhor to flatter.</l>
               <l>Beſides the ſeuerall voyages which he made</l>
               <l>Againſt the Spaniſh foe, which would inuade</l>
               <l>Our Brittiſh coaſt: the ciuill warres of France</l>
               <l>Drew forth our Engliſh <hi>Scipio</hi> to aduance</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:18314:6"/>
               <l>His colours there, which he diſplaid, and wonne</l>
               <l>Honourable knighthood, when the fight was done.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henrie</hi> the 4. of France in gracefull manner,</l>
               <l>Vpon deſert confer'd this warlike honour.</l>
               <l>And fame imprints this Character on his ſhield,</l>
               <l>Knighted by <hi>Burbon,</hi> in the open field.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deſert neglected, droopes; encourag'd, beares</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Its motions well, as the well ordered Spheares.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our minds proue then, beſt actiue, when we know</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our plants are ſet where they are like to grow.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The home-bred flames of France extinct, our owne</l>
               <l>Portend a hot combuſtion by <hi>Tyrone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Traitor, who like a Tyger gnawes</l>
               <l>The wombe which bare him, with his bloudy pawes.</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18314:6"/>
               <l>The Queene beſtow'd ſome fauours, and he thought,</l>
               <l>Had ſhe done more, s'had done but what ſhe ought.</l>
               <l>Through the perſpectiue of his fantaſie,</l>
               <l>He dream'd he ſaw his vertues grow ſo hie;</l>
               <l>That, part of <hi>Vlſter,</hi> for the great <hi>Oneale,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was not ſo fit, as was a common-weale.</l>
               <l>So, by ambitious proiects, look't for gales</l>
               <l>Which might fill full, and yet not rent his ſailes.</l>
               <l>Among the valiant chieftaines which were ſent</l>
               <l>To ſtop the current of his proud intent,</l>
               <l>Came <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> whoſe acts did carrie ſenſe,</l>
               <l>And weight of honour with experience.</l>
               <l>His colours flew with ſuch anſpitious fate,</l>
               <l>As if that faire <hi>Bellona</hi> there had ſate</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18314:7"/>
               <l>With wreathes of gold to make a crowne for him,</l>
               <l>Who harboured prowes in each manfull limbe:</l>
               <l>And made him after his victorious triall,</l>
               <l>The Sergeant Maior of the armie royall.</l>
               <l>The Lord <hi>Mountioy,</hi> Lord deputie of that realme,</l>
               <l>Who ſate as Pilot in that dangerous healme,</l>
               <l>Wrot to the Lords in England his opinion,</l>
               <l>Touching the ſafetie of that ſicke dominion.</l>
               <l>Becauſe experience taught him oft to learne,</l>
               <l>That boggs and faſtnes made the Iriſh kerne</l>
               <l>To neſtle in the North, he did propound,</l>
               <l>That ſome one man whoſe iudgement was profound</l>
               <l>And valour matchles, might haue forces readie</l>
               <l>To curbe the rebells at the firſt, if headie</l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18314:7"/>
               <l>Attempts ſhould moue them to an inſurrection,</l>
               <l>Or draw them (as they ſpeake) to go in action:</l>
               <l>For this imployment (ſo records affirme,</l>
               <l>And il'e de liuer it in it's proper terme)</l>
               <l>Sir <hi>Arthur Chicheſter is the fitteſt man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Saies he) <hi>in England or in Ireland,</hi> can</l>
               <l>Fame be more copious in her bountie: then</l>
               <l>To praiſe his worth aboue a world of men?</l>
               <l>That campe had many worthies who ſuruiue,</l>
               <l>And liue to ſee their reputation thriue.</l>
               <l>Yet all with ſamous <hi>Mountioy,</hi> doe agree</l>
               <l>To write in that of <hi>Chicheſter, this is he:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But now they write <hi>he was,</hi> from whence abound</l>
               <l>Our flouds of griefe like Spring-tides to ſurround,</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18314:8"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tyrone</hi> himſelfe, whoſe lewd affections ſtood</l>
               <l>To croſſe, with malice, the increaſe of good:</l>
               <l>Who lay in wait with vnappeaſed ſpleene,</l>
               <l>In ſecret ambuſhments, to wrecke his teene</l>
               <l>On carefull <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> did proteſt, ſo many</l>
               <l>Parts of a Souldier were in him, that any,</l>
               <l>Who leade in warlike marches, could not be</l>
               <l>More iuſt, more valiant, nor more wiſe then he.</l>
               <l>Thoſe flames of good deſert muſt ſparkle hie,</l>
               <l>Whoſe brightnes is approu'd by enmitie.</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Brittains</hi> Monarch read his true <hi>Eſſay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In a faire copy, for a beaten way</l>
               <l>Was made by Fame, which in the <hi>Preſence</hi> told</l>
               <l>The King in earneſt, Ireland did hold</l>
               <l>Such faire eſteeme of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> that he might</l>
               <l>Safely preferre him to maintaine his right</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18314:8"/>
               <l>In that adioyning and vnciuill Nation,</l>
               <l>The King thinkes on it and approues the motion.</l>
               <l>The Poſt took leaue, &amp; brought backe certain word,</l>
               <l>An honoured Gentleman ſhould receiue the Sword.</l>
               <l>Fame thou art ſodaine, and maiſt erre; in this</l>
               <l>Ile take my oath thou neuer wentſt amiſſe.</l>
               <l>Almoſt twelue yeares in ſuch a gouernment?</l>
               <l>If ages paſt can ſhew a preſident,</l>
               <l>I am deceiu'd: ſuch rules of requity</l>
               <l>Were drawne forth by his hand, as piety</l>
               <l>Gaue order for: That learning which was poore,</l>
               <l>Found meanes to helpe it ſelfe out of his ſtore.</l>
               <l>Vertue did meet with Honour; and Religion</l>
               <l>With Wiſdome, it with Bounty: all in <hi>One,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:18314:9"/>
               <l>Valour reioyc'd to find a ſure protection,</l>
               <l>Vpon the word of his braue inclination,</l>
               <l>Which ſet an edge on Courage, when it found,</l>
               <l>A gracious hand to beare it from the ground.</l>
               <l>He lou'd both Arts and Armes: iuſt ſuch another</l>
               <l>As <hi>Pembrokes</hi> Vncle, or as <hi>Leiceſters</hi> Brother.</l>
               <l>A <hi>Sydney,</hi> a <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and that's as much,</l>
               <l>As to write in plaine Engliſh, a <hi>None ſuch:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For in good ſooth neuer before or ſince,</l>
               <l>Could a Vice-roy doe more honour to his Prince.</l>
               <l>The people praid, <hi>Lord if it be thy will,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let this Lord be Lord Deputy with vs ſtill.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I ſeeke not to detract, <hi>Boetius</hi> ſaies,</l>
               <l>Good is diffuſiue and hath ample praiſe,</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:18314:9"/>
               <l>To giue this man his due, and yet retaine</l>
               <l>Good ſtore for others, when it giues againe.</l>
               <l>One writes, the Deputies of that Kingdome are</l>
               <l>Like Aple-trees, and if their fruit be faire,</l>
               <l>The Cudgels then muſt flye: T'was ſo with him,</l>
               <l>For ſome Informers, whoſe aſpect was dimme,</l>
               <l>Who ſee no right, nor can diſcerne religion,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe i'th habite of their ſuperſtition,</l>
               <l>Tax him of much iniuſtice, by a rabble</l>
               <l>Of falſe ſuggeſtions at the Councell table.</l>
               <l>But Royal <hi>Salomon</hi> did obſerue the cauſe,</l>
               <l>And found 'twas not his Deputy, but his Lawes</l>
               <l>Were call'd in queſtion: therefore daign'd to giue,</l>
               <l>Words which might make a dying man to liue.</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:18314:10"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>This man is cleere,</hi> vpon examination,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I finde that all's an vniuſt accuſation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With other Princely ſpeeches which tranſcend,</l>
               <l>Nor can they, as they ought, by me be pen'd:</l>
               <l>When <hi>innocence,</hi> his trueſt <hi>aduocate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Made replication to the Plaintiffes hate;</l>
               <l>And that the Agents for their falſe report,</l>
               <l>Should vndergoe the Cenſure of that Court;</l>
               <l>His meekeneſſe followed and beſought the King</l>
               <l>To pardon his accuſers, who did bring</l>
               <l>Their owne diſgrace, not his: a rare example,</l>
               <l>In theſe malitious times, inimitable.</l>
               <l>They ſought his ruine, he their good: we ſee</l>
               <l>The leſſon kept, Chriſt taught him, <hi>learne of mee.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18314:10"/>
               <l>When the Kings pleaſure order'd his remoue</l>
               <l>From that high place, the State with generall loue,</l>
               <l>Bade him farewell, that euery acclamation,</l>
               <l>Seem'd a diſcreet and ſtudious Oration</l>
               <l>To ſpeake in order of thoſe noble parts,</l>
               <l>Which were the Loadſtone of the Iriſh hearts.</l>
               <l>His credit had iuſt intereſt to aſſume</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſiahs</hi> bleſſing, as a <hi>ſweet perfume,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which being odoriferous in ſent,</l>
               <l>Fills all the ſtanders by with much content.</l>
               <l>His name ſounds iuſt as when one ſweetly ſings,</l>
               <l>To tunefull muſicke on harmonious ſtrings.</l>
               <l>No praiſe, but whats exact, can fit his ſpirit,</l>
               <l>Whoſe faire compoſure did conſiſt of merit.</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18314:11"/>
               <l>In theſe daies Vertues lodge apart, but he</l>
               <l>Prepar'd one lodging where they all might be:</l>
               <l>I meane, his pious and couragious breſt,</l>
               <l>Where all the Graces built their common neſt.</l>
               <l>His naturall gifts had tenures on condition</l>
               <l>To yeeld to Grace: for his good diſpoſition</l>
               <l>Held it vnequall in it's wiſe <hi>Idea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Rachel</hi> ſhould ſubmit to bleare-ey'd <hi>Leah.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cheere vp my Muſe, and flye aloft to raiſe,</l>
               <l>A laſting Colume by thy towring Laies.</l>
               <l>Inſcribe vpon it, <hi>Chicheſter:</hi> for that word</l>
               <l>Is a large Tombe of goodneſſe; a Record</l>
               <l>Of honour, wit, experience, valour, worth,</l>
               <l>And Time's the Filizer to produce it forth.</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18314:11"/>
               <l>It ſignifies a <hi>Captaine</hi> or a <hi>Knight;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Sarjeant Major</hi> when the Armies fight,</l>
               <l>A princely <hi>Vice-roy,</hi> a Lord <hi>Treaſurer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or elſe the Germane Lord <hi>Embaſſadour,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In England a great States-man: and to end,</l>
               <l>Truths Champion, Arts encourager, Valours friend,</l>
               <l>All which employments doe preſent a taſt</l>
               <l>Of ſeuerall honours in my Lord <hi>Belfaſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe happy <hi>Genius</hi> being put in action,</l>
               <l>Drew forth the view of publike admiration.</l>
               <l>One night, not long ſince, in the skie was ſhowne,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Star</hi> depending on the forked <hi>Moone:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But now the <hi>Moone</hi> waites on the glorious <hi>Starre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe brightnes doth ſurpaſſE the Moon-ſhine far.</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18314:12"/>
               <l>Honour and Life, like to the <hi>Moone,</hi> haue waines,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt is the morning ſtarre:</hi> in piercing paines</l>
               <l>Of death, this Lord diſdain'd the <hi>Moones</hi> reſpect,</l>
               <l>For the felicity of the <hi>Starres</hi> elect:</l>
               <l>He did confeſſe, like that Diuine S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Chriſt was his gaine, his hope, his life, his all.</l>
               <l>His Tongue was tipt with golden ſentences,</l>
               <l>Which recollect the Soule, when her offences</l>
               <l>Haue made her thoughts vnſteaddy, that ſhee ſtands</l>
               <l>Giddy, like the foun dation on the ſands,</l>
               <l>Vntill that Word of God afford a light,</l>
               <l>To put the Soule in a more hopefull plight.</l>
               <l>The goodly ſtructures which were framed by</l>
               <l>The curious platformes of his induſtry,</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:18314:12"/>
               <l>In earthly things, he did conclude were winde,</l>
               <l>And ſubiect to corruption: that his minde,</l>
               <l>Empty of her owne good, might mount vp higher,</l>
               <l>Whither a Chriſtian ought for to aſpire.</l>
               <l>The Angels were on wing, to beare away</l>
               <l>His ſoule, and yet he argues, their delay</l>
               <l>To be o're long; lamenting his aboad</l>
               <l>Was yet on earth, diuided from his God.</l>
               <l>Each faculty of his ſoule ſtriu'd which ſhould be</l>
               <l>Beſt learned in the ſchoole of piety.</l>
               <l>Zeale mou'd as liuely in thoſe chriſtian ſtraines,</l>
               <l>As blood encloſed in the narrow veines.</l>
               <l>To ſee him dye, was dolour: thus to dye,</l>
               <l>Rauiſh't the Mourners with alacrity,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they ſaw, he went a glorious Gueſt,</l>
               <l>At Supper-time, vnto the <hi>Mariage feaſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:18314:13"/>
               <l>Thus he expir'd; nor could a humane Creature,</l>
               <l>With more content diſcharge a debt to Nature.</l>
               <l>England laments: and where his body goes,</l>
               <l>That Land is drowned with a Sea of woes.</l>
               <l>Would I might liue here ſtill, the Iriſh Shores,</l>
               <l>Will be as gloomy as the tawny Moores:</l>
               <l>Their blacke-dide countenance will miſinforme</l>
               <l>The skillfull Pilot: and as in a ſtorme,</l>
               <l>Confuſion will ſucceed; for beds of ſand,</l>
               <l>Will moue the waues to driue them toward land,</l>
               <l>That they may vie their multitudes with <hi>All,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who ſhed a teare at his ſad Funerall.</l>
               <l>Tis well <hi>Knockfergus</hi> ſtands vpon a rocke,</l>
               <l>For otherwiſe the fierce impetuous ſhocke</l>
               <l>Of diſmall out-cries when the Corpes come thither,</l>
               <l>Will make the Fort, and Wall, and houſes ſhiuer,</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18314:13"/>
               <l>Or crumble into duſt, like <hi>Iericho,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When <hi>Ioſuahs Rams hornes</hi> were obſeru'd to blow.</l>
               <l>Yea the whole Realme will make a dolefull cry,</l>
               <l>To make an Earth-quake for his <hi>Elegie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The ſwift wind will be reaſty, as afraid</l>
               <l>To waft the noiſe, leſt all the land be made</l>
               <l>Subiect to ruine, in aſtoniſhment,</l>
               <l>With much bewailing this dire accident.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioy-mount</hi> can be no mount of ioy, but moane,
<note place="margin">The name of his houſe at Knockfergus.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Like to the Turtle when her mate is gone.</l>
               <l>The Drums and Fifes clad in their mourning ſuite,</l>
               <l>Will ſound, as if his death had made them mute.</l>
               <l>The aire will be all blacke, and like a Fuller,</l>
               <l>Dye the light Banners in a ſable colour.</l>
               <l>The buriall muſt be wet, ſith no eye's dry,</l>
               <l>I'th ſwelling deluge of this miſery.</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:18314:14"/>
               <l>Among the preſſe, my <hi>Muſe</hi> deſireth roome,</l>
               <l>To ſpeake one word to him, who makes the Tombe:</l>
               <l>Be ſure to cut his Eare <hi>indifferent;</hi> and</l>
               <l>A golden Pen in his laborious hand.</l>
               <l>Shew forth his eyes with ſuch reſplendent light,</l>
               <l>As one who ſtill retaines his wonted ſight.</l>
               <l>As for his Robes of Parliament, let them be</l>
               <l>Put on with ſuch aduice, that we may ſee</l>
               <l>His Sword, and know a Souldier: on his Armes</l>
               <l>Write this; <hi>The Bucklers to defend from harmes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His Prince and Countrey.</hi> And beneath his head</l>
               <l>A Pillow, as if he were gone to bed.</l>
               <l>Thou maiſt limme Honour, ſpeaking; <hi>This is he,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whoſe braue exploits hath thus deſerued me.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let it not be, as if he ſought for her,</l>
               <l>For that will wrong the King, who did preſer</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18314:14"/>
               <l>His Deputy, of himſelfe; and gaue th'impreſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ile honour him, who ſought for nothing leſſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Honer ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fugien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Make his Tombe wide and high, to imitate</l>
               <l>The copious circle of his ample fate.</l>
               <l>If in thy fabricke thou doſt want a ſtone,</l>
               <l>Sith griefe hath made me <hi>Niobe,</hi> Ile be <hi>one.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I wiſh this happineſſe to his Heire; <hi>Inherit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like to Eliſha, this Eliahs ſpirit:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For that's a ſtately impe of Fame, by which</l>
               <l>More honour is, then is, by being rich.</l>
               <l>Lord, What is man? when ſuch a man as he,</l>
               <l>Whoſe parts excelled in the high'ſt degree,</l>
               <l>Dies by a <hi>Pluriſie,</hi> a corrupted tumour,</l>
               <l>Proceeding from a bad vnhealthfull humour.</l>
               <l>How ought we then, who are but Atoms ſmall,</l>
               <l>And in reſpect of him, are not at all,</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18314:15"/>
               <l>To know our bodies but an houſe of earth,</l>
               <l>And thinke on God before the ſoule goes forth?</l>
               <l>His laſt to me was this; <hi>Much thankes, Good night.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May my beſt ſeruice ſtudy to requite</l>
               <l>His noble complement: For it I returne,</l>
               <l>Millions of teares on his bewailed Vrne.</l>
               <l>And fith, the bed he ſleepes on, is his Biere,</l>
               <l>Ile bid, <hi>Good night,</hi> and draw the Curtaines here.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18314:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
